<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Tyler Benning Product Designer]]></title><description><![CDATA[The portfolio and stories of Tyler Benning ]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com/</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 00:53:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Motivations Assessment]]></title><description><![CDATA[Overview Paddle is a seed funded startup that offers career exploration tools. The first product offering is a self assessment tool that…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/paddle-motivations-assessment/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/paddle-motivations-assessment/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paddle is a seed funded startup that offers career exploration tools. The first product offering is a self assessment tool that helps you understand your motivations and recommends industries suited to what will motivate you. The second offering is a learning platform that aids user’s next steps in learning about these industries. The product helps users to build their career path and keep them motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.mypaddle.co/warmup&quot;&gt;Paddle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Projects I worked on&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 February: Paddle Branding &amp;#x26; Logo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 March-May: Motivations Assessment MVP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 May-July: Next Steps Career Library&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 August: Marketing Emails HTML/CSS Templates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 August: Premium Paywall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 September: Soft Launch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 December: Pitch Deck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 October-December (full-time): Paddle 2.0 Overhaul&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Team&lt;/strong&gt;
We had a small team focused on the product. Through our cross-discipline design activities, everyone at Paddle had a say when designing and building the next product features. We moved quick and made decisions together on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our small team looks like this:
CEO Business Development / Content
Product Manager / Content
Two Developers
Product Designer
Co-op Student&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had ownership over the design of the product from end-to-end. As the first non-founder hire at an early stage startup, I was able to wear multiple hats and work closely with the founders to turn their vision into something more tangible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a t-shaped designer means I did a variety of things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research &amp;#x26; usability testing
Product design thinking &amp;#x26; workshops
Interaction design (my vertical!)
UI design &amp;#x26; style guide
Branding &amp;#x26; marketing
HTML/CSS fixes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being at a startup = Entrepreneurship 101. Over evening drinks, late nights in the office, and seeing the general comings and goings, I got a great feel for the entrepreneurial spirit. I’ve grasped many new aspects of how a business is run, and what it takes to build something valuable that people want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, my new favourite reads are Paul Graham’s essays (even if I don’t agree with him all of the time). I think about the future and what products will exist there. I’ve become obsessed with new products on Product Hunt, up and comers on Angel List, and the latest funding on Crunchbase. Entrepreneurship culture is neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html&quot;&gt;Essays&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design-driven companies are becoming the norm thanks to the likes of Google Ventures, AirBnb, and more. I used my time at Paddle as an opportunity to share my knowledge about how to use design as a tool for business. I helped make sure they could take a design-driven approach to building their business, by putting the user first and testing early and often!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Career Path Explorer]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’ve worked with Paddle since early 2016, when the company had just began. I helped them launch their first self-assessment tool, and…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/paddle-explore-roles/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/paddle-explore-roles/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked with Paddle since early 2016, when the company had just began. I helped them launch their first self-assessment tool, and continued to consult with them in my spare time over the coming years. I’ve worked on everything from product design, to conference banners, to pitch decks with the team. We’ve developed a great relationship over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2018, Pat the CEO, took me out for a beer and enlisted my help for a new product they wanted to work on, which would help promote internal mobility at large enterprise companies. The product was still in its infancy and they needed help to turn a vision and a bit of research into a product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got ready to put my facilitator hat on, and started preparing to kick off a 3 day problem discovery workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three Days to Discover&lt;/strong&gt;
The team had already done some preliminary research with customers, employees, and managers to understand how internal mobility and careers at large companies worked. We used this qualitative data to make a user journey map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[JOURNEY MAP HERE]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the product was still in its nascency, we did an activity to articulate a a vision statement to guide to the team as we moved forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Vision IMG]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this journey map we identified high and low level problems that employees and managers might face when looking at internal movements. We diverged to condense these problems into grouped themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[GROUPED THEMEs]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent the next session working on different solutions for these problems. At IBM, I’d learned an exercise called “big ideas” which are a helpful way to articulate solutions that weren’t too feature driven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[IMAGES HERE]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After voting on our favourite ideas, we started sketching out bigger ideas on our own. This lead to a smattering of good ideas that we could continue to reference as the product progressed. We still have this backlog of ideas posted up in the office. If you work on a product and you keep circling back on a similar idea, it’s usually a good sign that it might be a promising feature for your product. Sometimes you just have to sit back and listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[IMAGES]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we had worked through a good storyboard (thanks to AJ&amp;#x26;Smarts helpful hacks!), I took the designs away and started to create hifi designs that we could use to test with customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User Testing&lt;/strong&gt;
The worst thing you can do is think of an idea and build the whole product without talking to any users or customers. One of the other team members Ankur took the lead on user testing and getting customer feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After talking to some customers, we saw a need that we could fill with one of our previous ideas “Internal Roles Board”. In this idea, users could discover and learn about different roles that existed in the company, then eventually apply to jobs in these roles at the right time. It fit in perfectly with the other ideas we had, but allowed for a better end-to-end experience that felt like a complete enough MVP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UI Design&lt;/strong&gt;
Before I got to involved in building out UI mocks, I wanted to make sure the developers and I were on the same page, so we could build the UI efficiently using a shared system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found out the the developers had made some decisions around front end architecture. We would use a blended Design System that took advantage of Semantic UI for major components. I had some flexibility to modify Type, Colors, and icons. We would build some simple components on our own, and implement Styled Components to customize some semantic UI components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.styled-components.com/&quot;&gt;styled-components&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, I worked on a couple of iterations building out some simple UI concepts. I passed the assets off in Zeplin for the developers to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Launch&lt;/strong&gt;
We’re still in the early phases of launching it with one of their current customers. We meet weekly to talk about progress, user adoption, UI fixes, iterative work, and to prioritize what to work on next.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Front-End Prototyping]]></title><description><![CDATA[At Top Hat, we’re in higher education. Higher education works in semesters. So we work in semesters. Each semester we have something called…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/top-hat-eng-week/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/top-hat-eng-week/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;At Top Hat, we’re in higher education. Higher education works in semesters. So we work in semesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each semester we have something called Engineering week. Engineering week is the time that everyone stops doing product based sprint work and focuses on a list of projects proposed and pitched by engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a dinky metaphor to share that I stole from the Eng leads. Say you’re in a forest chopping trees, but you never have time to sharpen your axe because you’re always too busy chopping trees. Engineering week is the time to stop and sharpen your axe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year in the winter semester, I pitched, planned, and led my own engineering week project, notably titled FE4 Prototyping . I pitched it as a chance to use our component library to build simple front-end prototypes (and as a bonus become best friends with me for a week 👬).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior developer Jeremy jumped at the chance to be my best friend, and took a chance on the first design led Engineering week project. I estimated t-shirt sizes for the project and mapped out different projects that could be worked on, big and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/radius-engineering/project-estimation-through-t-shirt-size-ea496c631428&quot;&gt;Project Estimation Through T-Shirt size – Radius-Engineering – Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy and I settled on a simple project to set up a create-react-app and use our front-end library to build an improved course lobby. I’d lead the design, and also implement it with Jeremy’s coaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did a bit of research to understand the data behind how the lobby was used. After a quick request to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;#analytics&lt;/code&gt; Slack channel, I found some useful data on how many courses users have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[img here]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out lots of users have &gt;4 courses, so I thought it might be nice to improve the UI with a list view that users could toggle to. I wanted to tighten up some other UI details while I was at it, and add some other helpful links to other Top Hat resources that often get missed by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy spent the first day setting up &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;create-react-app&lt;/code&gt; with our front-end library. There were hiccups along the way. While Jeremy showed me how to set up my dev environment, I wrote up a ReadMe for others to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the next couple of days piecing together my design, getting coaching and mentoring from Jeremy along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We investigated other more complex projects, but made sure to finish the week with a tangible thing that we’d built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the week we had another team set up and use the front-end prototyping app for their own project!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[UX Quickwins on Mobile]]></title><description><![CDATA[As the lead designer for iOS and Android, I’d inherited UI that didn’t feel like it belonged to the same family as our web product. The…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/top-hat-ux-quickwins/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/top-hat-ux-quickwins/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As the lead designer for iOS and Android, I’d inherited UI that didn’t feel like it belonged to the same family as our web product. The typography, colours, and UI was messy and didn’t really follow a system. There were lots of small inconsistencies and interaction design issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[IMG HERE]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our mobile team was centralized and small. We had priorities to stabilize crash rates, keep up with new features being introduced to the product, and fix the app whenever there were new OS releases. Sprint after sprint, design kept getting put on the back burner as “something we’ll do once we finish up this other important work”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few frustrating months of trying to get buy in to prioritize a UI refresh, we agreed on an alternative approach that we now call &lt;strong&gt;UX Quick Wins.&lt;/strong&gt; Over the course of a year and a half, we slowly chipped away at design debt while continuing to do other important work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice something wrong in the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a JIRA ticket to fix it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a design, show it to the developers and other designers, and iterate on the design based on feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attach a new design to the ticket&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get it bundled into the next sprint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another infrastructural piece that was missing was common tooling between design and development. We weren’t speaking the same language, and I noticed we were spending a lot of time determining colours, typography, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Top Hat, every semester we have one week called &lt;strong&gt;Engineering Week&lt;/strong&gt;. During this week, the devs have the opportunity to stop chopping down trees, and instead sharpen their axes and work on infrastructure. During this week I worked closely with the mobile developers to set up a proper design system of styles that we would build from. This would reduce the effort when passing off designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created rules around&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spacing (8pt grid system with 16pt margins)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colour palette&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Icon system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enforce this system we used Zeplin to create the library of styles, and drafted a ReadMe in Github. I even downloaded Xcode and Android Studio to dig into their styles and patterns and remove unnecessary colours, icons. After engineering week, I now had the ability to pull branches of work, run a simulator, demo, and give feedback to the developers when needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this system was put in place, our UX Quick Wins started rapidly picking up speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log In Flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join Course Flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Course Lobby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empty States and Illustrations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classroom answered/unanswered + tree state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gradebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigation titles + Icons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we’re still working on UX quick wins and it’s not over yet. Here are some examples of improvements we’ve been able to make over the past year, all while stabilizing the infrastructure, reducing crash rates, and keeping up with projects from other teams.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[My Kid Years]]></title><description><![CDATA[I grew up in the boonies in a farmhouse and had too much time to kill.
When I was 7, my brother taught me how to use our family computer. I…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//about/kid-years/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//about/kid-years/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I grew up in the boonies in a farmhouse and had too much time to kill.
When I was 7, my brother taught me how to use our family computer. I
quickly discovered how magical computers can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started playing games like Doom, Command &amp;#x26; Conquer, Warcraft, and
SimCity daily. I learned to download music and burn mixed CDs to
impress friends at school. My friends’ parents started asking me to
fix their computers, and I even made a bit of money doing it. I
learned to use audio interfaces to record music, DV cameras to make
videos, and how to play around with graphics in Photoshop. I wasn’t a
child prodigy programmer, but I was a bit of computer whiz that could
learn new tools quick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, my brother taught me about HTML. He showed me that if you
write in a notepad file and save it with &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; at the
end, that the computer recognizes it as a web page. A couple of inline
styles and anchor tags later, and my Dragon Ball Z drawings and MS
paint renderings soon materialized into a homemade DBZ fan page.{’ ‘}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things have happened from now since then (namely Myspace, bad
haircuts, puberty, university, a career) but I still get lost inside
my computer tinkering around and learning new ways to conjure things
onto the screen.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Portfolio Site]]></title><description><![CDATA[How I Designed This I approached this project similarly to how I approach most design projects. Figure out who the users are and their tasks…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//personal-projects/tylerbenning-website/tylerbenning-website/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//personal-projects/tylerbenning-website/tylerbenning-website/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;How I Designed This&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I approached this project similarly to how I approach most design projects. Figure out who the users are and their tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, based on the conversations I’ve had around my last portfolios it’s probably:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recruiters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring managers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other designers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mom ❤️&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I expect people to use this site for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skimming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Judging Me 🧐&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimizing for Reading &amp;#x26; Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so users are supposed to spend time reading and learning on this site. What kinds of sites are optimized for reading? Well, I’d been reading and learning from loads of documentation sites like React, Gatsby, Mozilla docs, so I looked at their patterns. Documentation sites usually have clear an straightforward navigation to get guide users through content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sketched out a few simple layouts on paper, structured out my content, then started mocking them up in Sketch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose a sidebar navigation that listed out my different project write-ups. When a user is done reading a writeup, they can hop over to the next item on the sidebar. There’s no need to go back to the main project page, scroll down, and find the next one. Sure, it only really saves a quick click here and there, but it adds up when you’re short on time and trying to flip between write-ups. I also added keyboard navigation for lazy people and power users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visual Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did some photoshop magic on my hero image and added in some fun mixed media illustrations that I pulled from a pattern on my favourite shirt. I grabbed my personal logo I’d made a few years ago and plunked the SVG into my Sketch file. Nothing special. Just enough to add some fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Typography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is a content site, I made the typography straightforward with large headings in IBM Plex Sans, that I paired with Google Font’s PT Serif. It’s amazing what a little CSS can do to really make a site shine. &lt;a href=&quot;https://perfectmotherfuckingwebsite.com/&quot;&gt;Perfect Motherfucking Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“How I Built This”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost a decade ago, I’d spent a good deal of time learning HTML/CSS, Javascript, and a bit of PHP. I’d built some Wordpress site, and a couple of other rudimentary sites, before diving headfirst into a career in design, leaving coding (mostly) behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2018, I decided I’d test the waters and look at how front end tools have evolved. I started learning git, set up a Github, and enrolled in a Javascript course at HackerYou. I started compiling a huge list of resources and used this roadmap as a guide on what to learn. It turns out there’s a good amount of resources for designers who want to learn more code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kamranahmedse/developer-roadmap&quot;&gt;GitHub - kamranahmedse/developer-roadmap: Roadmap to becoming a web developer in 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to have projects while learning. After I’d completed a few jQuery assignments (project 1, project 2) for my HackerYou course, I wanted to dive into React and figure out what all the buzz was about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started taking some online tutorials from Wes Bos and Meng To to get a feel for React. I read through all the Gatsby docs, and decided to use Gatsby as my tool of choice. I installed Styled Components and Prettier, and started structuring out my content in markdown files. I picked up just enough GraphQL to grab data from my markdown files, and get my site up and running on Github Pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m using LightHouse to check features.
I’m still working on accessibility. It’s an important facet of design and development that I’m really curious about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Content Writing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write everything using Bear. I found it a few months back, and write all my work and personal notes in it. There’s a handy feature where you can copy everything as markdown, so I just paste everything I write into my markdown files on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, there are more elegant CMS’, but I don’t mind updating my markdown files manually and pushing them to Github to deploy my site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been a wild ride getting this thing going, if you’re curious about the source code for this site, check the project out on Github. I always appreciate feedback on how I can improve the quality of this site.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Launching an Open Source Brand]]></title><description><![CDATA[My friend from work Jake has pioneered the open source initiative at work, and has been getting more involved in different projects and…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//personal-projects/all-contributors/all-contributors/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//personal-projects/all-contributors/all-contributors/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;My friend from work Jake has pioneered the open source initiative at work, and has been getting more involved in different projects and communities. He’s the guy that pops up at designer’s desks to ask for logos, UI mocks flag and coffee mug designs for sometimes-neat-ideas he’s stewing over. This wasn’t the first time Jake has asked me for a favour, and likely won’t be the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jake:&lt;/strong&gt; Hey Tyler, wanna do a logo for something. Check it.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/all-contributors&quot;&gt;All Contributors · GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyler:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, okay. I’ll sketch a couple ideas and wrap something up tomorrow night. I’m leaving for vacay at the end of the week, so I’ll see if I can pump out some quick ideas before I go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can I say? I’m a sucker for enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After work, I lazily browsed the repo, scrawled some shapes in my notebook, and made a few shitlogos that felt uninspired and weren’t very good. I called it a night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, I actually &lt;strong&gt;read&lt;/strong&gt; about the project, and realized it was a pretty neat idea that already had a good amount of traction. Bring everyone and their contributions into GitHub’s open source community. Get all hands on deck for open source projects, and motivate more people across different disciplines to contribute. Lower the barriers for adding contributors. Leave no contributor behind!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait. I actually love this idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling refreshed, I went through another quick round of designs about an hour before hopping on a flight to Costa Rica. I quickly sent a mock of ~10 logos to Jake. Because it was 3AM, I guess Jake wasn’t awake, so I pulled the trigger and sent an SVG of what I thought worked best. I knew I wouldn’t have a laptop on vacation, and sometimes you’ve just gotta go with your gut. My Uber was downstairs and I had to get going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the logo pays homage to the ✨ emoji that the project owner Kent Dodds had used on the project since it started. We wanted to build on it, but add more flair and “revolutionary” symbolism ;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a bit of time to think while sipping Imperial lagers on the beach. I’d been doing some research on open source communities for a work project, and I decided that I wanted in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyler:&lt;/strong&gt; I want to get more involved with the project. Let’s chat when I’m back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jake:&lt;/strong&gt; Right-o! Chat ya when you’re back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following weekend I sat down with Jake and got him to explain All Contributors to me as simply as possible. He told me about the existing project, and the bot that he’d built to add contributors to the ReadMe page of your repo. I try to get people to repeat things and teach me a concept until it’s simple enough for anyone to grasp. Then I repeat it back to them to check if it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the brain dump, I took this information and wrote a draft of content for a homepage. Since it’s a marketing page, the goal is to concisely teach users how it works, and then them to install the Github Bot. Simple marketing magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few hours later I had a Sketch mockup finished, so I sent it around the All Contributors Slack group to get some feedback. Next day I cloned the website repo, and coded the page directly inside the Docusaurus app. I made a pull request, got it reviewed, and a few days later the site was up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the project, tell your friends, and try out the bot on your own Open Source project!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Loss Event Entry]]></title><description><![CDATA[Problem Picture this. You manage a team of currency traders at a large bank and you find that one of your team members made a mistake while…]]></description><link>http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/ibm-loss-event-entry/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://tbenning.github.io/tylerbenning.com//work-projects/ibm-loss-event-entry/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture this. You manage a team of currency traders at a large bank and you find that one of your team members made a mistake while trading currencies that cost your department $50,000. At this point, it’s your team’s responsibility to report a loss event to the risk management team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you do next? Who do you tell? Who’s accountable? How do you collect more information? What system do you need to use to record the information?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;😅😅😅&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting loss events at banks can be scary. You’re stressed about the mistake that was made, and now you have to figure out the rigorous process to report it to the risk team. In an ideal world, everyone in a company would work together to report loss events, but communication problems, team silos, and difficult pieces of legacy software prevent teams from working together and submitting these events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our customers needed an elegant solution for infrequent and non-users of OpenPages to submit loss events quickly and easily, so that they could improve risk management practices across the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was the team lead and user experience designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Located in Toronto, our team of 4 worked remotely with the OpenPages product management and development teams in Massachusetts and Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My responsibilities included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coordinating remotely with our Product Manager and Developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborating on initial research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitating customer-facing workshops for problem discovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team sketching sessions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low fidelity prototyping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testing prototypes for validity and usability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presenting design “playbacks” to our remote teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team was usually juggling multiple projects at once. Loss Event Entry is one of about eight projects I worked on with the OpenPages team, which we completed over the course of 3 months from initial scope to completion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dylan, our user researcher and I lead design activities with teams at two separate “Big Five Banks” in Toronto. We facilitated journey mapping exercises to map out the loss event process in different teams. We learned a lot from the study, but the participants were surprised to find that they learned more about their own processes throughout the exercise!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a few emergent themes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ad Hoc Processes&lt;/strong&gt;
Events are documented and submitted in ad-hoc processes, which change across the business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt;
It’s necessary for different actors to work together when collecting information about a loss event.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usability matters&lt;/strong&gt;
We found an internal tool that was built to capture loss events, but was failing to do the job properly because it was over 100 inputs long, with no helper text, and 90% of the fields were mandatory. &lt;em&gt;Nobody used it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design &amp;#x26; Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a designer, I believe it can be important to ideate without major constraints to understand an ideal user-centred solution, and then scale back based on constraints. It’s important to expand the teams understanding of what’s possible, but also take a balanced perspective to come to a good compromise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learned what our users needed, but we also needed to decide what was the essential job that our product could fulfill, and what was extra. To understand the technical constraints, I worked with the development team to get a sense of what types of information we could access to via their REST API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put together a user journey and low fidelity mocks of the ideal solution. We worked with our Product Manager Bob, and our technical leads to undergo various rounds of iteration and feedback to come to a good solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working Within Constraints&lt;/strong&gt;
We stripped down the collaborative features, and built a form that users could work through incrementally. We made only absolutely necessary fields required, and added an area for helpful tool tips. We used progressive disclosure, so that users could work through bitesized chunks of data input, and skip areas that didn’t apply to their type of loss event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our UI designer Jasmine picked a colour scheme, type scale, and spacing that would work well to balance that information architecture but also adhere to the IBM Design Guide. She worked closely with our front end developer Susan to build a simple front end prototype in Angular, which we brought back to customers to perform user testing. We found usability improvements and workflow improvements that we were able to get into the production build of the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was finished with a few weeks to spare, so we had the appropriate time to test and get extra UI polish and copywriting changes into the final version.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>